521 Cherry Street Wrightsville, PA 17368 717-575-2503 717-252-2672 S2Hagen@aol.com

OBJECTIVE: To acquire an administrative position in a highly successful educational community.

EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

Offering 13 years of Administrative Achievement in Developing Productive Student-Focused Environments to Maximize Learning Experiences

DIRECTOR OF CURRICULUM AND INSTRUCTION TURN-AROUND SPECIALIST MIDDLE SCHOOL PRINCIPAL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL PRINCIPAL

Dedicated, resourceful education professional with proven ability to create and monitor policies and practices that promote a positive and safe learning environment; ensure a school culture that encourages continuous improvements for teachers and students; develop an environment that encourages open communication with colleagues, students, and the community; and mentor educators in the creation and implementation of class instruction, lesson plans, and student assessment in conjunction with state learning regulations.

"Administrators should have fortitude, balance, and a calm presence in relating to the various stakeholders with an organization or school/district. Ms. Sharon Hagenberger consistently demonstrated these qualities while serving in the roles of Middle School Principal, the Director of Curriculum & Instruction, and the Turn-Around Specialist of New Hope Academy Charter School... Sharon Hagenberger would be a cornerstone to any administrative team.."

Carrie Adams Soliday
Professional Development Specialist
Lincoln Intermediate Unit 12

EDUCATION

Drexel University Technology Integration Certificate - 4.0 G.P.A.

Philadelphia, PA Current

Pennsylvania State University Principal Certification - 4.0 G.P.A. **Greater Malvern, PA** 1999 Millersville University M.Ed. - 3.8 G.P.A.

Millersville, PA 1992

Millersville University B.S. Ed. - 3.3 G.P.A.

Millersville, PA 1983

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

New Hope Academy Public Charter School **Director of Curriculum and Instruction Turn-Around Specialist** Middle School Principal

York City, PA 07/2012 to present

10/2011 - 07/2012

- Design & manage all instruction and curriculum for 745 students in grades 5-12 in a public charter school with newly developed and rewritten PA Common Core and Legal Standards with multiple discipline integration, ELL and Special Education Accommodations, Project-based assessments, and Cornerstone Assessments included for each unit for Language Arts, Social Studies, Science, and Math.
- Design all Professional Development and provide training for 54 professional staff, 30 paraprofessionals, and 3 Administrators.
- Manage the \$1.6 million dollar School Improvement Grant.
- Manage all major assessments Keystone Exams, PSSA Exams, PSAT/SAT Exams, Accuplacer Exam, NAEP Tests, CDT's (Classroom Diagnostic Tools), Scholastic Reading & Math Inventories, Aims-web, and 4Sight Exams for the Middle School and High School Complex.
- Implement and manage the RTII program for Grades 5-8.
- **Implement and manage the new teacher Induction program** and Boot Camp.
- Train and manage the Professional Learning Community Facilitators and four PLC teams.
- Manage the PA-Etep online Teacher evaluation in the Danielson model as well as observing and evaluating 15 teachers per semester. Also complete 82-1 Evaluations and training for teachers and administrators on the SLO plans.
- Participate in Staff recruitment and hiring
- Manage technology and arts integration, online assessments, and "Blended" online E2020 Courses for students in grades 5-12.
- Complete all State required reports: Comprehensive Plan-Phase II; Annual Charter School Report; School Improvement Grant Reports; AMAO Improvement Plan and Report; and the SPP School Improvement Plan for SIG recipients.

Donegal School District **Elementary and Primary School Principal**

Mount Joy, PA

Planned, controlled, and directed the overall activities for an elementary school and a kindergarten center with 402 students, 37 professional staff, and 24 non-professional staff. Scope of position included: staff recruitment; teacher development and evaluation; fiscal management; records and administration organization and maintenance; student discipline; program initiatives;

02/2000 to 06/2010

team-building; shared decision-making; school values promotion; advisory council coordination; and creation of a safe, respectful, and fair environment.

- Met AYP in all buildings each of the ten years of administrative duties.
- Reduced student discipline by 60% through the implementation of a Positive Behavior Plan and "Principal's 100 Club".
- Reduced the number of nurse referrals by 50% and food waste through the implementation of a specialized lunch schedule and playground program.
- Wrote, designed, and produced all building instructional plans, intervention strategies, building communications (Monday Memo, etc.), student and staff handbooks, and acted as webmaster for all building websites.
- Successfully managed Response to Intervention teams for grades K-5, Instructional Support teams, Positive Behavior teams, Autism Select teams, two Parent-Teacher organizations, and chaired the district's Technology committee for Strategic Planning.
- Worked with architects to design plans for the construction of four elementary schools, and one intermediate school.
- Acted as the District Coordinator for Technology Integration with IU#13, and the "Blended Schools" on-line initiative.
- Wrote and acquired grants for the purchase of technology hardware for the district.

Northeastern School District

Manchester, PA

Music Teacher/Choral Director/Instrumental Teacher

08/1988 to 02/2000

Central York School District

York, PA

Middle School/Elementary Music/Choral Director

06/1987 to 08/1988

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Curriculum Council monthly meetings with York/Adams IU#12
Teachscape Teacher Evaluation Certification – Danielson Model
Keystone Exams, PSSA, and Classroom Diagnostic Tools Administrator Training
105 Hours of intensive leadership training through the State
"Principal's Inspired Leadership" program.
Leadership training with Dr. Robert Marzano.

Response to Intervention and Instruction Select Team training IU#12 & 13

Autism Select Team training

Success by Six training

PBIS - Positive Behavior Intervention System training PVAAS training

Zocklein Grant Writing Training

FEMA Certification for Administrators

Technology Integration Specialist certification - 9 of 18 credits at Drexel University.

PAEtep Online Teacher Observation Training SAS Annual Conference – 2011, 2012, 2013

AMAO Training for Improvement Planning 2013

SIG- School Improvement Grant Training 2012, 2013

SPP- Training for School Improvement Planning 2013

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT:

Manage the 21st Century Grant After-School Program with the YWCA
Manage the Parent Advisory Committee for the SIG Grant
Assist in the management of the New Hope Performing Arts program at the Strand Capital
Performing Arts Center in York City

Managed the K-Kids program with the Rheems Kiwanis - 4 years Coordinated the building of new playgrounds in the borough of Mount Joy and Marietta, PA- 4 years